Guide to the Land use and planning documents, San Mateo and Santa Clara Counties, 1958-1995
Department of Special Collections
Land use and planning documents, San Mateo and Santa Clara Counties,
1958-1995
Special Collections M0912
Crowder, Elizabeth S. (Betsy), collector.
4 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Crowder served as Palo Alto City Planner from 1972-1982 and was on the Portola Valley Planning Commission from 1974-1982. From 1987 to 1997 she was a member of the San Mateo County Trails Advisory Committee. She was an elected member of the Board of Directors for the Mid-Peninsula Open Space District from 1989 to 2000, the date of her accidental death. The collection consists primarily of reports and other publications regarding land use in California, particularly in San Mateo and Santa Clara Counties, 1958-1980.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Betsy Crowder, 1997.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Mid-Peninsula Regional Open Space District.; Palo Alto Planning Commission.; Stanford University--Planning.; Land use--Planning--San Mateo County (Calif.); Land use--Planning--Santa Clara County (Calif.); Palo Alto (Calif.)--Planning.; Portola Valley (Calif.)--Planning.; San Francisco Bay Region--Conservation of natural resources.
Biography
Betsy Crowder, a native of Massachusetts, received and MA from Radcliffe College in English literature in 1947, and move to California in 1948. She has lived in Portola Valley since 1960. Crowder returned to school and received an MA in Engineering and Urban Design from Stanford in 1972. She served as Palo Alto City Planner from 1972-1982 and was on the Portola Valley Planning Commission from 1974-1982. From 1987 to the present (1997) she has been a member of the San Mateo County Trails Advisory Committee. She has been the Elected Director of the Mid-Peninsular Open Space District since 1989.
Scope and Content
The Betsy Crowder Collection consists mainly of reports and other publications regarding land use in California, especially in San Mateo and Santa Clara Counties. These materials are filed by the name of the city or county they most specifically pertain to, and are alphabetized by title within these categories. The collection also includes various pamphlets and other items regarding the British New Towns; these are filed together by town name. Two "notebooks" comprise the last major part of the collection. These notebooks are groups of reports, notes, and newspaper clippings pertaining to Crowder's city planning activities and other land use issues. The contents of these notebooks are roughly organized as arranged by Crowder.
Container List
- Series 1. United States Reports and Publications
  - California, general
    - California Division of Mines and Geology Centennial 1980 (Box 1)
    - Erosion and Sediment Handbook 1978 (Box 1)
    - Filling in the Blanks: Using Unused Urban Land1981 (Box 1)
    - Historic Ground Failures in Northern California Associated with Earthquakes 1978 (Box 1)
    - Land Use, Open Space, and the Government Process: The San Francisco Bay Experience 1974 (Box 1)
    - Local Government Planning Survey 1979 (Box 1)
    - Permit Guidelines 1979 (Box 1)
    - An Urban Strategy for California 1978 (Box 1)
    - Water Conservation in California 1976 (Box 1)
  - Palo Alto
    - Palo Alto Baylands Master Plant List 1973 (Box 1)
    - Palo Alto Baylands Master Plan and E.I.R. 1978 (Box 1)
    - Comprehensive Plan Background Reports 1975 (Box 1)
    - Palo Alto Comprehensive Plan for 1977-1990 1976 (Box 1)
    - Foothills Fire Hazard 1968 (Box 1)
    - Hewlett Packard Environmental Impact Report 1979 (Box 1)
    - Palo Alto Noise Control Program 1974 (Box 1)
    - Parks and Recreation Policy Study 1969 (Box 2)
    - Sand Hill Road Supplemental Revised Environmental Impact Report 1978 (Box 2)
    - Willow Road Improvement Project Environmental Impact Report 1975 (Box 2)
  - San Mateo County
    - Master Plan Proposal 1958 (Box 2)
    - Proposed Corridor Plan for a State Scenic Highway: Skyline Boulevard1967 (Box 2)
  - Santa Clara County
    - Soil Survey 1958 (Box 2)
    - Soil Workshop 1977 (Box 3)
  - Stanford
    - maps (Box 3)
    - Land Use Permit Modification Draft Environmental Report 1986 (Box 3)
    - Pearce Mitchell Houses 1975 (Box 3)
    - Report on Urban Planning Curricula for Division of Architecture and Urban Design in the Department of Civil Engineering 1972 (Box 3)
  - Federal and Miscellaneous
    - Caring for the Land 1977 (Box 3)
    - Maintaining Subsurface Drains 1972 (Box 3)
    - Performance Controls for Sensitive Lands 1975 (Box 3)
    - Planning for Wildlife in Cities and Suburbs 1978 (Box 3)
    - Subdividing Rural America1976 (Box 3)
    - Wildlife Planning Glossary 1978 (Box 3)
- Series 2. Items regarding British New Towns
  - British New Towns
    - Town Planning in Britain since 1945 1971 (Box 4)
    - British New Towns: 1 (album) (Box 4)
    - British New Towns: 2 (album) (Box 4)
  - British New Towns, pamphlets, general
    - Garden Cities of To-morrow 1965 (Box 4)
    - The National Trust for Scotland in the Seventies 1971 (Box 4)
    - The New Towns 1970 (Box 4)
    - The New Towns of Britain 1969 (Box 4)
    - Third International Tour of British New Towns 1971 (Box 4)
    - Town and Country Planning 1971 (Box 4)
  - British New Towns, pamphlets, by town
    - Basildon 1972 (Box 4)
    - Crawley 1970 (Box 4)
    - Haverhill n.d. (Box 4)
    - Hemel Hempstead (1 of 2) 1969 (Box 4)
    - Hemel Hempstead (2 of 2) 1970 (Box 4)
    - Letchworth (1 of 2) 1968 (Box 4)
    - Letchworth (2 of 2)1969 (Box 4)
    - Greater London Services 1971 (Box 4)
    - Petersborough ca. 1970 (Box 4)
    - Stevenage 1971 (Box 4)
    - Thetford ca.1970 (Box 4)
    - Welwyn Garden City (1 of 3)1959 (Box 4)
    - Welwyn Garden City (2 of 3)1970 (Box 4)
    - Welwyn Garden City (3 of 3) 1970 (Box 4)
- Series 3. Oversized publications
  - The Urban Design Plan for the Comprehensive Plan of San Francisco 1971 (Box 5)
  - Preliminary Regional Plan for San Francisco Bay Region 1966 (Box 5)
  - LIFE Magazine12/24/65 (Box 5)
  - LOOK Magazine9/21/65 (Box 5)
- Series 4. Crowder Notebooks
  - Notebook #1 (in a Stanford folder), items regarding Stanford University Land Use, in particular the 1988 proceedings with the Palo Alto Planning Commission: the review of the general use permit, and the drafting of an Environmental Impact Report (EIR):1975 - 1995 (Box 5)
    * Whole issues of Stanford Community Report, 1984-1988 -- * Whole issue of The Stanford Earth Scientist, 1987 -- * Clippings from The Progressive, Palo Alto Weekly, Stanford Campus Report, The Country Almanac, Stanford Community Report and unidentified papers, 1975-1995 -- * Notes, memos, minutes and reports (Palo Alto Planning Commission, 1988)
  - Notebook #2 (originally in a "Carlyle" binder), publications, clippings, notes and reports regarding Stanford land use issues. ca. 1984-1988 (Box 6)
    Items are loosely organized under the following headings: S.U. General [permit] and Processes -- Stanford West -- On Campus building -- S[anta] C[lara] County Lands -- Sand Hill Road